I love strength training and I'm not the
biggest fan of cardio I don't really
enjoy running it's so incredibly clear
if you only do one of those modes
strength training or endurance you're
leaving a lot of Health in the table
well what is like a minimal
effective routine then that doesn't
require one to be a professional athlete
and dedicate all of their free time to
exercise
like is it important to differentiate
between the different exercise
modalities and this is my answer would
have been yes and here's the reason why
at least differentiating between
strength and cardiovascular endurance is
critically important because they're
independent predictors they will stack
on top of each other but they're also
independent we also have so much data
from lifelong exercisers um this is some
work I've done and published um
colleagues of mine have done this is a
paper that came out just in the last
couple of weeks that showed this but
it's so incredibly clear if you only do
one of those modes strength training or
endurance you're leaving a lot of Health
in the table and so this is why I would
make that argument you really do need to
have both of them they're independent um
they are helping you stay alive for
different reasons we have the direct
evidence of these lifelong exercisers
that they're just not in the best place
if they don't do ball I love strength
training and uh I'm not the biggest fan
of cardio I don't really enjoy running
is vigorous walking a sufficient
replacement no no it's not it's better
than nothing again if we're talking
about what is least bad versus optimal
um so I don't want you to hear that and
think all right that's it I'm out like
I'm done right it's not an excuse to not
do it um if if vigorous walking is all
you can get into that's great that's
like Z what some people refer to as zone
two yeah I don't care what zone like
you're in at all um that's like very
little concern to me generally I think
it's clear that you need to be doing
something that requires you to sustain
energy output at a higher than resting
rate for long periods of time okay
Define that as Zone whatever you want I
don't really care again I have friends
that are like so deep into Zone 2
they've made careers out of this amazing
like that's great you want to pull your
blood and figure out what your lactate
levels are that's amazing I don't really
care um I have other ways we pay
attention to that but that's fine you
need to clearly be able to sustain
exercise or energy output that's
elevated for a long period of time what
might that look like I mean are jogging
bike riding sure hiking it could be a
vigorous walk any of those things I
think what's important to understand
here is it's not the of exercise that
matters it rarely is right it's a
physiological demand so what you need to
be doing is asking for an Advanced
Cardiovascular rate that is sustained
with no break that's all we're after the
mode and Method you pick is entirely up
to you on the surface it's irrelevant to
this aspect of physiology it's very
relevant to other parts joint health or
movement patterns personal preference uh
availability to stuff fine but right now
for this physiological output we just
simply care about asking a sustained
input unless you're an athlete or have a
specific specific muscle you're want to
work at for injury prevention or
recovery or for if you're an aesthetic
sport exercise is not really about the
output it's the input that matters right
it's what's the physiological demand the
easy way to think about this is um the
physiological limiter will be the place
of adaptation so what I mean by that is
wherever in your physiology is asked to
fail is going to be the place that
adapts so in this particular case if
you're saying hey we're struggling to
maintain a 25% increase in output of
exercise of energy and we're struggling
to maintain that wherever part of your
physiology is struggling is going to
adapt so maybe that's your breathing
maybe that's the mechanics of your
posture maybe that has nothing to do
with that and it is your ability to
bring in utiliz fat as of fuel maybe has
nothing to do with that and it is your
gate and how you're walking and that's
why your knee is hurting that's why
you're like it could be any number of
things so that's if it is a situation
where you're like man every time I walk
or jog lightly I get these back injuries
then don't do that anymore it's not
worth it right find another way to ask
for cardiovascular demand find a way
that is not leading to injury if you
care to fix your running dat great if
you don't then don't don't worry about
it right like whatever is in for you the
same thing with our athletes that have
short demands on performance right so if
we have a competition six weeks from now
it's the same thing this is still an
investment in six weeks from now right
we're going to be needing to do this for
a lot of reasons outside of that you
clearly need to be able to perform at a
high heart rate as well this can be done
in any number of ways short high
intensity intervals like think your
classic 20 30 40 seconds maybe up to a
minute of hard work some sort of matched
recovery maybe this is less recovery
than work so maybe this is 60 seconds of
hard work and 30 seconds of rest maybe
it's the opposite 30 seconds to work
more rest they're they're different that
gives you a little bit of fun stuff I
actually think people should do like a
combination of these maybe it's a little
bit longer two or three minutes of
sustained work two or three minutes of
rest like fine you're challenging your
ability to go to a Max or near max heart
rate that is going to ask different
physiological demands than the lower
intensity stuff so by leaving that stuff
out of the equation you are leaving
adaptations out the equation just like
by only going red line only going high
heart rate max heart rate and not doing
anything at a moderate or lower is also
leaving things off the table so I really
think you need both it's it's hard to
come up with a situation in which both
of them combined at some point are not
advantageous H well what is like a
minimal
effective routine then that doesn't
require one to be a professional athlete
and dedicate all of their free time to
exercise to achieve to achieve these
these adaptations minimum effective dose
is a little bit different because you
need to think about are we talking
maintenance of current status or are we
talking about actual Improvement right
so maintenance of current status it is
insanely low uh if you were to do say
one strength training workout every two
weeks or so that's probably sufficient
to maintain muscle size and strength
interesting it can be very very low
you're talking about even a few sets
total over a couple of weeks um there's
actually a good amount of research on
that that you can sustain decent amount
of strength can you optimize and
increase probably not cardiovascular
output would be the same actually this
is actually kind of fun if you look at
speed to strength to endurance and then
muscle mass is a very clear progression
or or reduction of these over time such
that speed is hard to maintain uh if you
really want to maximize power output
this will fall off fast it will fall off
fast with dra trining and it'll fall off
fast with age so if you were to plot
World Records in things like the
marathon compare those to World Records
in strength based sports like
powerlifting and you compare that to
World Records in sprinting and you look
at what happens to those world records
as we go from age 30 to 35 to 40 kind of
in 5year increments the speed ones will
drop off the reservation like they're
just gone really fast you will not see
somebody who is a competitive World
Sprinter at 45 you can absolutely see a
competitive endurance athlete in fact
many of the world records won't happen
until folks are 30 35 or so years old
wow and that the the difference between
the world record of a 50-year-old versus
a 35y old it's like not much but if you
look at that 100 milard dash it's like
the difference between 9.58 and and like
12 seconds it's like a just a it's not
even in the stratosphere of competitive
so speed will go off fast strength will
go off fast but maintaining hypertrophy
and maintaining endurance is really
really simple we actually did a study
years ago looking at taper in Cross
Country Runners so this is really cool
these were College competitive College
cross country Runners and we did
biopsies of them uh we did V2 max
testing we did an actual uh competition
and we looked at them pre and post three
weeks of taper now over the course of
that taper they ended up reducing
running volume by
50% BO2 Max didn't go anywhere stayed
the exact same right no change uh we
looked at a number of markers in muscle
tissue of aerobic capacity um none of
those moved no reduction whatsoever we
saw an improvement of performance though
they ran faster in the post raised they
did so we lost no cardiovascular markers
whatsoever up and down we looked again
we looked at them all over the place we
did though see a dramatic increase in
the size and I think it was about nine
or so percent of the fast switch muscle
fibers so we see a large increase in
fast muscle fiber size with 3 weeks of
reduced training H they cut their
training in half and saw and they were
terrified by the way W cuz like
endurance Runners like you take mileage
away and they're like really but we saw
nothing so the point The Grand Point I'm
making there is is endurance is fairly
stable very minimal doses if you were to
do one again I don't know the an exact
paper here um but if you were to do one
session say 30 seconds on 30 seconds off
maybe four of those right so repeat that
four times you did that once every
couple of weeks I would imagine it would
probably keep your V2 Max reasonably
close click the link in our bio to get
instant and free access to our
hypertrophy highlights fireside chat
which is Dan and I discussing really
personal aspects of how we go about
programming for muscle hypertrophy in
that chat you're going to hear Dan and I
talk about our own experiences working
with clients who are trying to add
muscle mass and especially you're going
to hear us tell some stories that you've
never heard us talk about in any podcast
ever before this is not something
something you're going to want to miss